<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Andrew Morgan &#8211; Andrew Morgan on Databases</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/andrew-morgan/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Database technologies - especially around scalability and High Availability</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2009 09:40:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>Webinar replay available: What’s New in the Next Generation of MySQL Cluster?</title>
		<link>/mysql-cluster/webinar-replay-available-whats-new-in-the-next-generation-of-mysql-cluster</link>
					<comments>/mysql-cluster/webinar-replay-available-whats-new-in-the-next-generation-of-mysql-cluster#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2009 09:40:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[MySQL Cluster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Andrew Morgan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cluster Database]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MySQL Cluster 7.0]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MySQL Cluster CGE]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=112</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is another live webinar on MySQL Cluster 7.0 scheduled for 27th May 09:00 (Western European time) / 08:00 (UK time) / 11:00 (Eastern European time) and you can register here. Alternatively, if you can&#8217;t wait that long then you can watch/listen to the play-back of the original webinar. Note that you may need to]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is another live webinar on MySQL Cluster 7.0 scheduled for 27th May 09:00 (Western European time) / 08:00 (UK time) / 11:00 (Eastern European time) and you can <a title="MySQL Cluster 7.0 Webinar" href="http://www.mysql.com/news-and-events/web-seminars/display-350.html" target="_blank">register here</a>.</p>
<p>Alternatively, if you can&#8217;t wait that long then you can <a href="http://www.mysql.com/news-and-events/on-demand-webinars/display-od-320.html">watch/listen to the play-back of the original webinar</a>.</p>
<p>Note that you may need to <a title="WebEx Installer" href="http://www.webex.com/downloadplayer.html" target="_blank">install the WebEx Player</a> (Windows and Mac) &#8211; unfortunately, there doesn&#8217;t seem to be a simple, supported solution for LINUX users but you can always download the slides (PDF format) from the same link or else wait until 27th May and view it live.</p>
<p><span><span style="font-weight: bold;">What’s New in the Next Generation of MySQL Cluster?</span></span><span><br />
Thursday, April 30, 2009</span></p>
<p>Whether you’re racing to introduce a new service, or trying to manage an avalanche of data in real time, your database has to be scalable, fast and highly available to meet ever-changing market conditions and stringent SLAs.</p>
<p>By attending this webinar, you will learn more about MySQL Cluster 7, and how it enables you to deliver 99.999% database availability, with real time performance and linear scalability, while slashing TCO.</p>
<p>Boasting a range of breakthrough capabilities, the MySQL Cluster 7 will enable you to stay ahead of your most demanding, mission-critical application requirements. Enhanced scalability delivers higher database performance with fewer nodes to simplify deployment and administration. Expanded platform support and interoperability delivers more choice in both the development and deployment of MySQL Cluster. Simplified cluster monitoring tools reduce DBA administration overhead and operational costs.</p>
<p>Presented by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Andrew Morgan, MySQL Product Management</li>
<li>Matthew Keep, MySQL Product Management</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mysql-cluster/webinar-replay-available-whats-new-in-the-next-generation-of-mysql-cluster/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<link>/me/introduction</link>
					<comments>/me/introduction#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2009 09:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Andrew Morgan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Database]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MySQL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MySQL Cluster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Replication]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://clusterdb.com/?p=3</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just a quick introduction to begin with. I joined Sun Microsystems in Feb 2009 to look after the product management for MySQL Cluster and MySQL replication. I started my career with Nortel (technically BNR which was the R&#38;D arm of Northern Telecom but everything later got merged and rebranded as Nortel). I was responsible for]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick introduction to begin with.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="544" height="507" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-7" title="Me with my kids" src="http://clusterdb.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/kids_small.jpg" alt="Me with my kids" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/kids_small.jpg 544w, /wp-content/uploads/2009/04/kids_small-300x279.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 544px) 100vw, 544px" /></p>
<p>I joined Sun Microsystems in Feb 2009 to look after the product management for MySQL Cluster and MySQL replication.</p>
<p>I started my career with Nortel (technically BNR which was the R&amp;D arm of Northern Telecom but everything later got merged and rebranded as Nortel). I was responsible for writing the original proprietary, in-memory database for Nortel&#8217;s HLR product. Later on, we used a number of 3rd party databases for the HLR (provisioning rather than real-time) and then HSS &#8211; starting with Oracle for the HLR and then SOLID but then settling on MySQL Cluster as the scaleable real-time database for the HSS.</p>
<p>When I left Nortel (via an IBM rebadging) I moved to Sun, hoping to use my experience as a MySQL Cluster customer to help the team build upon their strong product.</p>
<p>So far, so good &#8211; I&#8217;ve been really impressed both with the MySQL team and with how well the product is doing both with telco companies and others.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m planning on using this blog to publish technical content, publicise product information as well as anything else that crops up.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/me/introduction/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
