<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>3.2 &#8211; Andrew Morgan on Databases</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/3-2/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Database technologies - especially around scalability and High Availability</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 09:41:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>Analyzing Data in Microsoft Excel with the MongoDB Connector for BI</title>
		<link>/mongodb/analyzing-data-in-microsoft-excel-with-the-mongodb-connector-for-bi</link>
					<comments>/mongodb/analyzing-data-in-microsoft-excel-with-the-mongodb-connector-for-bi#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[MongoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[3.2]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Excel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mongodb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MongoDB 3.2]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ODBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sql]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Windows]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=4155</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are many great BI tools out there that enable powerful analytics and data visualization but sometimes the right tool for the job is the one you already have sitting on your laptop. MongoDB 3.2 introduced the MongoDB Connector for BI which presents an SQL API to allow BI tools to read data from your]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are many great BI tools out there that enable powerful analytics and data visualization but sometimes the right tool for the job is the one you already have sitting on your laptop.</p>
<p>MongoDB 3.2 introduced the <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/products/bi-connector">MongoDB Connector for BI</a> which presents an SQL API to allow BI tools to read data from your database in real-time. Typically, this functionality will be showcased with specialized tools such as <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/webinar/live-data-visualisation-with-tableau-and-mongodb">Tableau</a> but it’s equally applicable to Microsoft’s ubiquitous Excel.</p>
<p>This video demonstrates how to connect Excel running on Microsoft Windows to the BI connector and then fetch data from MongoDB.</p>
<div style="width: 480px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-4155-1" width="480" height="270" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="http://clusterdb.com/upload/BI_Connector_with_Excel.mp4?_=1" /><a href="http://clusterdb.com/upload/BI_Connector_with_Excel.mp4">http://clusterdb.com/upload/BI_Connector_with_Excel.mp4</a></video></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The instructions in the demo assume that you already have a MongoDB database running together with a configured instance of the MongoDB Connector for BI – the <a href="https://docs.mongodb.org/manual/products/bi-connector/">documentation</a> explains how to set that up.</p>
<p>Note that Excel is not able to handle the &#8220;.&#8221; character or capital letters in table of column names. To overcome this, it was necessary to edit the DRDL file produced by the mongodrdl tool to map names to lowercase equivalents and to replace each &#8220;.&#8221; (used to flatten embedded documents) with a &#8220;_&#8221;; this requires v1.1 or later of the BI connector.</p>
<p>The MongoDB Connector for BI is part of <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/products/mongodb-enterprise-advanced">MongoDB Enterprise Advanced</a>; it can be freely downloaded for evaluation – why not <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/download-center#bi-connector">try it out for yourself</a>.</p>
<p>More information on the BI connector as well as other MongoDB 3.2 features can be found in <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/collateral/mongodb-3-2-whats-new">MongoDB 3.2: What’s New</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mongodb/analyzing-data-in-microsoft-excel-with-the-mongodb-connector-for-bi/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="http://clusterdb.com/upload/BI_Connector_with_Excel.mp4" length="231116948" type="video/mp4" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Free Webinar: Document Validation in MongoDB 3.2</title>
		<link>/mongodb/free-webinar-document-validation-in-mongodb-3-2</link>
					<comments>/mongodb/free-webinar-document-validation-in-mongodb-3-2#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2015 22:27:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[MongoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[3.2]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Document Validation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mongodb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MongoDB 3.2]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I’ll be presenting a free webinar on Thursday29th Octover – the new Document Validation feature coming in MongoDB 3.2. Thursday, October 29, 2015 9am PDT &#124; 12pm EDT &#124; 4pm GMT One of MongoDB’s primary attractions for developers is that it gives them the ability to start application development without needing to define a formal, up-front]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Document_Validation_rule.png"><img decoding="async" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Document_Validation_rule-300x114.png" alt="Defining MongoDB Document Validation Rules" width="300" height="114" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-4110" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Document_Validation_rule-300x114.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Document_Validation_rule-1024x390.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Document_Validation_rule-900x343.png 900w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>I’ll be presenting a free webinar on Thursday29th Octover – the new Document Validation feature coming in MongoDB 3.2. </p>
<p>Thursday, October 29, 2015<br />
9am PDT | 12pm EDT | 4pm GMT</p>
<p>One of MongoDB’s primary attractions for developers is that it gives them the ability to start application development without needing to define a formal, up-front schema. Operations teams appreciate the fact that they don&#8217;t need to perform a time-consuming schema upgrade operation every time the developers need to store a different attribute.</p>
<p>Some projects reach a point where it&#8217;s necessary to define rules on what&#8217;s being stored in the database. This webinar explains how MongoDB 3.2 allows that document validation work to be performed by the database rather than in the application code.</p>
<p>This webinar focuses on the benefits of using document validation: how to set up the rules using the familiar MongoDB Query Language and how to safely roll it out into an existing, mature production environment.</p>
<p>During the webinar, you will get chance to submit your questions and get them answered by the experts.</p>
<p>The webinar is free but you need to <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/webinar/document-validation-in-mongodb-3-2">register in advance here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mongodb/free-webinar-document-validation-in-mongodb-3-2/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MongoDB Document Validation &#8211; London MUG charts</title>
		<link>/mongodb/mongodb-document-validation-london-mug-charts</link>
					<comments>/mongodb/mongodb-document-validation-london-mug-charts#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 15:37:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[MongoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[3.2]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Database]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[document]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mongodb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MongoDB 3.2]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=4109</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last night I preented on the MongoDB 3.2 Documentation Validation feature at the London MongoDB User Group meetup; the charts are shared here. Unfortunately, I didn&#8217;t record the demo and so you&#8217;ll have to grab me at a future MUG if you&#8217;d like to see that! Abstract One of MongoDB’s primary appeals to developers is]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last night I preented on the MongoDB 3.2 Documentation Validation feature at the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/London-MongoDB-User-Group/events/224606434/" target="_blank">London MongoDB User Group meetup</a>; the charts are shared here. Unfortunately, I didn&#8217;t record the demo and so you&#8217;ll have to grab me at a future MUG if you&#8217;d like to see that!</p>
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>One of MongoDB’s primary appeals to developers is that it gives them the ability to start application development without needing to define a formal, up-front schema. Operations teams appreciate the fact that they don&#8217;t need to perform a time-consuming schema upgrade operation every time the developers need to store a different attribute (as an example, The Weather Channel is now able to launch new features in hours whereas it used to take weeks). For business leaders, the application gets launched much faster, and new features can be rolled out more frequently. MongoDB powers agility. </p>
<p>Some projects reach a point where it&#8217;s necessary to define rules on what&#8217;s being stored in the database – for example, that for any document in a particular collection, you can be assured that certain attributes are present. </p>
<p>To address the challenges discussed above, while at the same time maintaining the benefits of a dynamic schema, MongoDB 3.2 introduces document validation.</p>
<p>There is significant flexibility to customize which parts of the documents are <strong>and are not</strong> validated for any collection.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/pRViHhcmzlQYTt" width="600" height="400" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe> </p>
<div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="//www.slideshare.net/andrewjamesmorgan/document-validation-in-mongodb-32" title="Document validation in MongoDB 3.2" target="_blank">Document validation in MongoDB 3.2</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="//www.slideshare.net/andrewjamesmorgan" target="_blank">Andrew Morgan</a></strong> </div>
<p>Please feel free to ask any questions through comments on this post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mongodb/mongodb-document-validation-london-mug-charts/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
